Katie Louchheim Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
- Subject File, circa 1934-1974 (Box 8-40)
  - National Federation of Business and Professional Women award, 1966-1969
  - Negro Student Fund, 1964-1968
  - Radcliffe College, Arthur and Elizabeth Schlesinger Library on the History of Women in America, Cambridge, Mass., 1951-1974, (5 folders)
  - Rockefeller Institute Public Service Award, 1964-1973 (Box 23)
  - Roosevelt, Franklin D., 1936-1946
  - Rosemary Hall, Greenwich, Conn., 1948-1974, (2 folders)
  - Smit, Leo, 1966-1970
  - Smithsonian Associates Ladies' Committee, 1967-1969
  - Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C., poetry readings, 1973-1974
  - Social events
    - Calendars, 1956-1972, (3 folders)
    - Luncheons and dinners, 1964-1972, (3 folders) (Box 24)
  - State Department
    - Administrative file
      - Ambassadors and their wives, 1961-1967, undated See also Classified, (2 folders)
      - American Legion, Special Liaison Committee report, 1964
      - Business advisers and consultants, 1965-1966 See also Classified
      - Chief of protocol, 1965-1968
      - Crockett, William J., 1964-1967 See also Classified, (2 folders)
      - Foreign policy reading file, 1963-1968 (Box 25)
      - Foreign Service Institute, Washington, D.C.
        - Programs, 1965-1968
        - Speeches to Junior Foreign Service Officers, 1965-1968
        - Wives' course, 1962-1969, undated
      - Foreign service wives
        - Association of American Foreign Service Women
          - Miscellany, 1961-1968, undated
          - Training course for wives, 1961-1968, (2 folders)
        - Publicity, 1961-1966
      - General correspondence, 1965-1969 (Box 26)
        - A-R See also Classified, (9 folders)
        - S-Z See also Classified, (3 folders) (Box 27)
      - Group lists, 1961-1965, undated, (2 folders)
      - Guest book, 1961-1969
      - Hays, Wayne, legislation regarding personnel system, 1965-1966, (2 folders)
      - Hebrew University, Jerusalem, Israel, 1963-1965 See also Classified
      - Katzenbach, Nicholas deB., 1966-1968
      - Letters (Box 28)
        - Appreciation for official entertaining, 1961-1968
        - Congratulations
          - 1961, (3 folders)
          - 1962
            - Received, (3 folders)
            - Replies
          - 1966-1967, (2 folders)
      - National Foreign Policy Conference for Educators, Washington, D.C., 1966 (Box 29)
      - Office of Women's Activities
        - Correspondence, policy, and printed matter, 1961-1965
        - Summaries of activities, 1961-1965
      - Public relations, 1962-1964
      - Reception Center, Miami, Fla., 1966-1967
      - Regional operations conferences
        - 1961
          - July-Aug., Nigeria, Cyprus, and India, (3 folders)
          - Oct., Peru and Costa Rica, (4 folders)
        - 1962, Baguio, Philippines See also Classified, (3 folders) (Box 30)
      - Reports and policy papers by Louchheim, 1961-1963, undated See also Classified
      - Rimestad, Idar, 1967-1969
      - Special projects
        - All countries, 1961-1966, (2 folders)
        - Ecuador, 1962-1966
        - Ghana, 1962-1964
        - Japan, 1963-1965
        - Malaya, 1961-1963
        - Nepal, 1961-1967
        - Niger, 1961-1963
        - Nigeria, 1961-1962
        - Pakistan, 1961-1962
        - Panama Canal Zone, 1961-1962
        - Ruanda-Urundi, 1961
        - Senegal, 1964-1965
        - Sierra Leone, 1961
        - Tanganyika, 1962
        - Thailand, 1962
        - Togo, 1961-1963
        - Tunisia, 1965-1966
        - Uganda, 1963-1966 (Box 31)
        - Yemen, 1961-1962
      - Status of Women Advisory Council and Interdepartmental Committee, 1962-1968
      - Unesco, 1966-1968
      - United States Advisory Commission on International Educational and Cultural Affairs, 1964-1969 See also Classified
      - White House memoranda, 1961-1967
      - Women and minorities in the foreign service, 1961-1964 See also Classified, (3 folders)
      - Women appointees
        - Lists, 1961-1966, undated
        - Recommendations, 1961-1968 See also Classified
      - Women for top positions, 1964-1966
        - A-F
        - G-Z, (3 folders) (Box 32)
      - Women's organizations, meeting on international programs, Washington, D.C., 1961
      - Women's programs, 1963-1966 See also Classified
      - Women's social and political lists, 1962-1968 See also Classified, (2 folders)
    - Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs
      - Advisory Committee on International Book and Library Programs, 1967-1968 See also Classified
      - Advisory Committee on the Arts, 1968, undated
      - American Specialist Program See also Classified
        - 1962-1967, (2 folders)
        - 1968, undated (Box 33)
      - Aspen Institute of Humanistic Studies, Aspen, Colo.
        - Ambassadors' reading program, 1966-1967
        - Executive seminars, 1965-1968
      - Background, 1963-1968
      - Board of Foreign Scholarships
        - Annual report, 1967-1968
        - Meetings and reports, 1966-1968, (2 folders)
      - Briefing papers, 1969
      - Budget requests, 1966-1968 See also Classified
      - Conference on the American Effort in International Educational and Cultural Activities, Washington, D.C., 1968
      - COSERV, National Council for Community Services to International Visitors, 1964-1968
      - Exchange programs (Box 34)
        - American Field Services, 1966-1968
        - Fulbright Scholarship Program, 1967-1968
        - Institute of International Education, New York, N.Y., 1966-1967
        - Student travel fares, 1966-1968
        - Teenagers, 1967
        - Travel restrictions, 1967-1968
        - University of Texas, Austin, Tex., and Universidad de Chile, Santiago, Chile, 1968
        - Volunteers to America, 1966-1968 See also Classified
      - Foreign student programs, 1967-1969
      - Foreign students, nonsponsored, 1967-1968
      - Frankel, Charles, 1966-1968
      - International Cooperation Year, 1964-1967 See also Classified
      - International visitors program, 1967
      - Job applicants, 1965-1968
      - Legislation, 1966-1967
      - National Association for Foreign Students, 1966-1968
      - Office space, 1966-1967
      - Policy statements, 1965-1968
      - Population and family planning, 1966-1967
      - Re, Edward Domenic, 1968 See also Classified
      - Reception areas, 1967-1968 (Box 35)
      - Reports, 1961-1968 See also Classified
      - Staff meetings, 1966-1968
      - Symposium on Education and Culture in Foreign Affairs Today, Washington, D.C., 1967
      - Trips
        - Europe, 1967
        - Miami, Fla., Council for International Visitors, 1966-1967
      - Vietnam orientation visits, 1967
    - Bureau of Public Affairs
      - Projects, miscellaneous, 1961-1965
      - Regional policy briefings on world affairs, 1961-1964
      - Trips
        - 1962
          - Europe
            - Correspondence and arrangements See also Classified
            - Itinerary and guest lists
            - Reports and follow-up See also Classified
          - Far East
            - Briefing book
            - Correspondence See also Classified
            - Itinerary and notes
            - Publicity (Box 36)
        - 1963
          - Greece, proposed trip
          - Spain
    - Office of Community Advisory Services
      - Films, 1965-1968
      - Foreign service wives' orientation, 1964-1968
      - Newspapers and periodicals for overseas posts, 1964-1966
      - Public relations television panel, 1962-1966
      - Regional Foreign Policy Conference, Milwaukee, Wis., 1964
      - Reports and correspondence, 1963-1969 See also Classified
      - Trip to Europe, 1965-1966
        - General correspondence
        - Places visited
          - Athens, Greece, and Rome, Italy
          - London, England, and Munich and Garmisch, Germany
        - Post-trip correspondence, notes, and clippings
        - Pretrip arrangements and guest lists
      - Wisconsin Trade Development Mission to Europe, 1965
  - Stay in School Fund Committee, 1963 (Box 37)
  - Stevenson, Adlai E. (1900-1965)
    - Campaign trips, 1956
    - Correspondence, 1952-1968
    - Memorials, 1965-1968
    - Speeches, 1952-1956
  - Truman, Harry S., 1955-1973 See also Container 8, same heading
  - United Nations, Seminar on the Civic and Political Education of Women, Helsinki, Finland, 1967
  - Unesco
    - Background information, 1966-1969, (2 folders)
    - Board members, 1968 See also Classified
    - Congratulatory letters, 1968-1969
    - Executive board
      - Meetings and social functions, 1969
      - Printed matter, 1968-1969 (Box 38)
    - Fifteenth General Conference, Paris, France
      - Correspondence, 1967-1969 See also Classified
      - Journal, notes, and resolutions, 1968
      - Printed matter and report to State Department, 1968-1969
    - General correspondence, 1968-1969
    - Personnel file, 1968-1969 See also Classified
    - Social functions, 1968-1969
    - State Department reports and memoranda, 1968-1969 See also Classified
    - U.S. National Commission for UNESCO, executive board meetings, 1968-1969
  - United Nations Relief and Rehabilitation Administration See also Containers 70-71, same heading
    - Meetings, memoranda, reports, and personnel file, 1943-1947, undated See also Classified, (2 folders)
    - Notebook, undated (Box 39)
    - Printed matter, 1945-1948
    - Scrapbook, 1943-1945
  - United Negro College Fund, 1965-1968
  - Washington Housing Association, Washington, D.C., 1947-1953
  - White House
    - Fellows' wives, 1967-1972
    - Guest lists, 1963-1968 See also Classified, (2 folders)
  - Women
    - African, 1966-1968
    - "Doer" lists of prominent women for White House events, 1963-1968
    - Equal Rights Amendment, 1970
    - Exhibits on historic contributions, 1961-1968
    - International, 1962-1966
    - Leaders among African Americans, 1962-1968
    - National Advisory Commission on Selective Service, 1966
    - Project for Promoting Political Understanding among German Women, 1962-1967 See also Classified, (3 folders) (Box 40)
    - Seminars
      - Proposed seminar on European and American women, 1965-1968
      - "Quo Vadis, Today's Woman," New York, N.Y., 1966-1967
    - United States-Soviet Union exchange program, 1958-1966 See also Classified, (2 folders)
  - Women's Bureau, Labor Department, press kit, 1970
  - Women's National Press Club
    - Annual dinner skits, 1946-1953, 1968
    - Correspondence, 1960-1965
  - Women's Week in Japan, 1965-1968
- Speeches and Writings File, circa 1937-1974 (Box 40-56)
  Correspondence; drafts of speeches, articles, books, short stories, novels, plays, and poetry; interview transcripts; scripts from radio and television appearances; and research material.
  Arranged alphabetically as interviews, radio and television appearances, speeches, and writings and therein chronologically.
  - Interviews (Box 40)
    - 1958, U.S. News and World Report
    - 1963, New Yorker profile
    - 1968, oral history, John F. Kennedy Library, Boston, Mass.
  - Radio and television appearances
    - 1961, Dec. 2, A Moment with.. ., television program
    - 1962 (Box 41)
      - Jan. 31, Radio Free Europe with Martin Bush
      - Feb.-Oct., Voice of America
      - Mar. 20, Here and Abroad, United States Information Service radio program
      - July 19, Opinion in the Capital with Martin Weldon
      - Sept. 8, with Harrison Williams
    - 1963, Sept. 9, Washington Viewpoint with Ann Corrick
    - 1964
      - Feb. 17, The Woman's Angle with Sylvia Scott
      - Mar. 29, Report to the People with Linton Wells
      - May 12, West German television with Renate Harpprecht
    - 1968, Feb. 21, Panorama, television program
    - Miscellaneous appearances, 1953-1968, (2 folders)
  - Speaking engagements
    - Background material
      - American women
        - Roles and careers, 1960-1969, (4 folders)
        - Volunteers (Box 42)
          - Abroad, 1962-1967
          - At home, 1961-1967
      - Educational and cultural affairs, 1960-1969, (2 folders)
      - Foreign policy, 1962-1968 See also Classified, (4 folders)
      - Humor and jokes, 1963-1966
      - Miscellaneous, 1960-1969 (Box 43)
      - Quotations, 1960-1969
      - Women in politics, 1960-1969, (2 folders)
    - Invitations regretted, 1963-1968
  - Speeches
    - 1953
    - 1954
      - Jan. 13, Adult Education Council Forum, Springfield, Mass.
      - Jan. 24, Democratic Women's Club, Greenwich, Conn.
      - Mar. 11, Democratic Women's Clubs of Kentucky, Louisville, Ky.
      - Mar. 15, Women's National Press Club, Washington, D.C.
      - Mar. 29-30, Democratic women's clubs meetings, Illinois
      - Apr. 7, Democratic Women's Conference, New London, Conn.
      - May 1, Democratic Women's Reception, Detroit, Mich.
      - May 19, Democratic Women's Day, Manchester, N.H. (Box 44)
      - May 25, Federation of Democratic Women, Philadelphia, Pa.
      - June 4, General Federation of Women's Clubs convention, Denver, Colo.
      - June 11-25, western tour
      - Aug. 2, Girls' Nation, American Legion Auxiliary, Washington, D.C.
      - Aug. 5, National Association of Colored Women, Washington, D.C.
      - Aug. 26, Farm Conference, Sioux Falls, S.Dak.
      - Sept. 18, Democratic Women, Indianapolis, Ind.
      - Oct. 16, Democratic women's clubs, Cincinnati, Ohio
      - Correspondence and miscellaneous speeches
    - 1955
      - Mar. 12, School of Politics forum, Washington, D.C.
      - Mar. 15-18, Democratic women's clubs, Illinois
      - Mar. 25, Democratic Women's Clubs of Davidson County, Nashville, Tenn.
      - Apr. 30, Democratic State Central Committee, Des Moines, Iowa
      - May 11, California
      - June 6, Lexington Democratic Club, New York, N.Y.
      - Aug. 5, Girls' Nation, American Legion Auxiliary, Washington, D.C.
      - Sept. 20, Workshop of New York County Democratic Women, New York, N.Y.
      - Oct. 21, Arizona Federation of Democratic Women's Clubs, Phoenix, Ariz.
      - Dec. 7, State Democratic Women, Augusta, Maine
      - Correspondence and miscellaneous speeches
    - 1956
      - Feb. 24, National Federation of Business and Professional Women, Washington, D.C.
      - Apr. 27, Democratic Women of Connecticut, Waterford, Conn.
      - May 7, Pennsylvania Federation of Democratic Women, Easton, Pa.
      - May 12, Democratic Women's Day, Lansing, Mich.
      - June 21, Democratic Women's Club, Huntington, W.Va.
      - July 11, Girls' Nation, American Legion Auxiliary, Washington, D.C.
      - Sept. 19, Democratic Women's Club, Plainfield, N.J.
      - Sept. 22, Women's Democratic Club, Bristol, Va.
      - Correspondence and miscellaneous speeches
    - 1957
      - May 13, National Cathedral School for Girls, Washington, D.C.
      - July 29, Girls' Nation, American Legion Auxiliary, College Park, Md.
      - Nov. 24, State Democratic Committee, St. Louis, Mo.
      - Correspondence and miscellaneous speeches
    - 1958
      - Jan. 5, Democratic Women of Chicago, Chicago, Ill.
      - Jan. 13, Maryland Women's Council, Washington, D.C.
      - Feb. 8, New Castle County Democratic Committee, Wilmington, Del.
      - Mar. 8, Democratic Women's Workshop, Charleston, W.Va.
      - May 15, Women's National Democratic Club, Washington, D.C. (Box 45)
      - May 22, Democratic Women's Suburban Symposium, Long Island, N.Y.
      - Correspondence and miscellaneous speeches
    - 1959
      - Apr. 17, National Education Association, Washington, D.C.
      - May 16, Jane Jefferson Clubs and Conference, Denver, Colo.
      - Oct. 15, Tenth District Democratic Women's Clubs, Arlington, Va.
      - Nov. 14, State Democratic Women's Convention, Orlando, Fla.
      - Nov. 20, Young Democrats and Democratic Women, Toledo, Ohio
      - Miscellaneous speeches
    - 1960
      - Jan. 5, National Women's Party, Washington, D.C.
      - Jan. 30, Federation of Democratic Women's Clubs, Fairfield, Conn.
      - Feb. 6, Western States Democratic Conference, Albuquerque, N.Mex.
      - Feb. 29, District of Columbia Young Democratic Club, Washington, D.C.
      - Mar. 1, Jewish Center Auxiliary, Akron, Ohio
      - Mar. 9, Zonta International, Washington, D.C.
      - Mar. 19, Rockland County Democratic Women, Suffern, N.Y.
      - Mar. 29, Women's Savings Bond Committee and the Advertising Club, Washington, D.C.
      - Oct. 18, Women's City Club, New York, N.Y.
      - Correspondence and miscellaneous speeches
    - 1961
      - Feb. 21, Business and Professional Women's Clubs of New York, New York, N.Y.
      - Apr. 9-10, National Council for Community Services to International Visitors, Columbus, Ohio
      - Apr. 15, General Alumnae Association, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, Pa.
      - Apr. 22, South Atlantic Region of the Soroptimist, Washington, D.C.
      - May 4, Young Women's Christian Association, Washington, D.C.
      - May 26, Coordinating Committee of Organizations Serving International Visitors, Washington, D.C.
      - June 8, General Federation of Women's Clubs Convention, Miami, Fla.
      - July 20-21, Regional Foreign Policy Conferences, San Francisco, Calif., and Denver, Colo.
      - Sept. 11, Missouri Federation of Women's Democratic Clubs, Jefferson City, Mo.
      - Oct. 1, Federation of Business and Professional Women's Clubs, Washington, D.C.
      - Nov. 17, National Council of Negro Women, Washington, D.C.
      - Correspondence and miscellaneous speeches
    - 1962 (Box 46)
      - Feb. 8, "Our Responsibility as Citizens," National Conference of Ladies Auxiliary, Veterans of Foreign Wars, Washington, D.C.
        - Mar., Japanese women's groups, Tokyo, Japan
      - Apr. 10, Wives' Club, National War College, Fort McNair, Washington, D.C.
      - Apr. 12, Women's Division, American Jewish Congress, New York, N.Y.
      - Apr. 27, United Fund Women's Council, Philadelphia, Pa.
      - May 7, Graduate Chapter, Alumnae Association, Radcliffe College, Cambridge, Mass.
      - May 22, Democratic Women's Campaign Conference, Washington, D.C.
      - June 20, White House Summer Interns, Washington, D.C.
      - June 28, General Federation of Women's Clubs, Washington, D.C.
      - July 28, World of Work Conference, Labor Department, Washington, D.C.
      - Oct. 1, "The Current American Scene," American Women's Club, London, England
      - Oct. 10, "The Role of Women in a Changing World," International Conference of Women's Activities, Berchtesgaden, Germany, (2 folders)
      - Nov. 14, "The American Woman as a Pacesetter," American Friends of the Hebrew University Women-of-the-Year Award, New York, N.Y.
      - Correspondence and miscellaneous speeches
    - 1963
      - Jan. 19, Women in Government luncheon, Washington, D.C.
      - Feb. 13-14, Foreign Policy Conference, Los Angeles and San Francisco, Calif.
      - Mar. 13, "Women on World Frontiers," Federation of Women's Clubs Overseas, Madrid, Spain
      - Apr. 20, "The Contribution of Women in a Changing World," Zonta International, Paterson, N.J. (Box 47)
      - Apr. 24, American Association of Foreign Service Women, Washington, D.C.
      - May 20, "The Contribution of Women in a Changing World," Temple Sinai Sisterhood, Washington, D.C.
      - June 9, "What Is an Education For?" Ohio University, Athens, Ohio
      - June 29, National Council of Women, Washington, D.C.
      - Sept. 30, World Affairs Conference, Albany, N.Y.
      - Oct. 12, "The Citizen in a Changing World," Catholic Daughters of America, Washington, D.C.
      - Oct. 19, "Women in a Changing World," College of New Rochelle, New Rochelle, N.Y.
      - Dec. 5, "The Real Americans," Phi Beta Kappa Society Alumnae, Washington, D.C.
      - Miscellaneous speeches
    - 1964
      - Jan. 24, Congressional Club panel, Washington, D.C.
      - Feb. 3, "Women in the Service of the Community and the Nation," Sisterhood of the Reformed Congregation of Keneseth Israel, Philadelphia, Pa.
      - Feb. 5, "Grassroots Diplomacy," Women's Forum on National Security, Washington, D.C.
      - Feb. 17, "The Real Americans," National Council of Jewish Women, Baltimore, Md.
      - Mar. 12, "Foreign Policy and the Individual," World Affairs Conference, Chapel Hill, N.C.
      - Mar. 21, World Affairs Conference, University of Wisconsin, Milwaukee, Wis.
      - Apr. 25, Theta Sigma Phi, Washington, D.C.
      - May 3, National Association of Negro Business and Professional Women, Brooklyn, N.Y.
      - May 9, "Opportunities for Women in Public Service," Georgetown University, Washington, D.C.
      - June 3, "On Distaff Diplomacy," Democratic Women's Club, Greenwich, Conn. (Box 48)
      - Aug. 19, Delta Sigma Theta, Washington, D.C.
      - Oct. 23, "The International World of the Individual," World Affairs Council, Cleveland, Ohio
      - Correspondence and miscellaneous speeches
    - 1965
      - Feb. 10, "In the Midst of Change," Sweet Briar College, Sweet Briar, Va.
      - Feb. 25, "The Citizen in a Changing World," Greater Wilmington Federation of Women's Organizations, Wilmington, Del.
      - Mar. 1, "In the Midst of Change," Adas Israel Congregation Sisterhood, Washington, D.C.
      - Apr. 8, "In the Midst of Change," American Women's Activities in Germany Conference, Garmisch, Germany
      - May 24, "The Council Woman's Place in the World," National Council of Jewish Women, Philadelphia, Pa.
      - June 28, "At the Heart of Diversity," Civitan International Convention, Washington, D.C.
      - Oct. 1, "The Constitution," Foreign Service Institute, Washington, D.C.
      - Nov. 9, "In the Midst of Change," Women's Canadian Club, Toronto, Canada
      - Nov. 17, Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, Tufts University, Medford, Mass.
      - Correspondence and miscellaneous speeches
    - 1966
      - Jan. 20, "Beauty Is Everyone's Business," National Institute of Traffic Engineers, Washington, D.C.
      - Mar. 7, "Today's Woman in Today's Changing World," Beth El and Chizuk Amun Sisterhoods, Baltimore, Md.
      - Apr. 2, Regional Foreign Policy Conference, Atlanta, Ga.
      - Apr. 20, "Today's Woman in Today's World," Junior League, Washington, D.C.
      - Sept. 15, "The View From Washington," American Men's Club, Paris, France (Box 49)
      - Oct. 15, "The Gift of Giving," Trinity College Alumnae Council, Washington, D.C.
      - Oct. 17, Business and Professional Women's Club, Houston, Tex.
      - Nov. 10, "The Longest Three Feet in the World," National Council for Community Services to International Visitors, Pittsburgh, Pa.
      - Correspondence and miscellaneous speeches
    - 1967
      - Feb. 1
        - Foreign Service Wives, White House reception, Washington, D.C.
        - Washington Post Book and Author Luncheon, Washington, D.C.
      - Feb. 3, Mary Baldwin College, Staunton, Va.
      - Feb. 13, Cosmopolitan Club, Philadelphia, Pa., poetry reading
      - Mar. 5, Immaculata Fathers Club, Washington, D.C.
      - Mar. 10, "The Challenge: Education for Cooperation," Southern Methodist University, Symposium on Education for Women, Dallas, Tex.
      - Apr. 3, "Are Men Becoming Obsolete?" American Society of Magazine Editors and Magazine Publishers Association, Washington, D.C.
      - Apr. 11, "Longest Three Feet," cultural and educational attachés, Washington, D.C.
      - May 18, "Value of Citizen Diplomacy," International Visitors Service Council, Washington, D.C.
      - May 25, Women Advertising Club, Washington, D.C.
      - June 2, American Field Students, Washington, D.C.
      - June 5, Senior Seminar in Foreign Policy, Washington, D.C.
      - Aug. 11, Writers' Conference, Georgetown University, Washington, D.C.
      - Sept. 21, "The Need for Leadership," Educational Press Association, Washington, D.C. (Box 50)
      - Oct. 24, "Partnership for Peace," United Nations Association, Fort Worth, Tex.